-==www.RagBear.com==-
福尔摩斯探案集  第1季第5集
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业用途
-=Keepfrds MNHD Team=- 校对: ptrpan
巴克利夫人 您的茶
Mrs. Barclay, your tea.
这么多年了 你怎么做得出这种事?
All these years, how could you do such a thing?
您的茶 夫人
Your tea, madam.
哦 我恨你 我恨你
Oh, I hate you, I hate you,
我恨你 恨死你了
I hate you, I hate you.
大卫...
David -
您的茶 夫人
Your tea, madam.
大卫 你背叛了他
David, you betrayed him.
范尼夫人...
Mrs. Fenning-
发生了什么事 怎么啦 孩子?
What's happened, what is it, child?
是夫人和上校
It's madam and the Colonel,
里面吵得吓人
something awful is going on
我打不开门
and I can't open the door.
让开 我来试试
Here, let me try.
快阻止他 你们两个
Stop him, both of you.
巴克利夫人
Mrs. Barclay,
巴克利夫人 快开门
Mrs. Barclay, open the door.
巴克利夫人 快开门啊
门从里面反锁了
The door is locked on the inside as well,
没有钥匙
and there's no key.
我去找医生 还有警察
I'm going out for a doctor, and the police.
驼背人案
他们人还不少
... There's quite a few of them
我受伤回家之前是
when I sailed home wounded.
他在印度功勋卓著
Had a good record out in India,
尤其平叛那两次 大获全胜
did wonders during the Mutiny.
你接手这个案子 肯定不会后悔的
I'm sure you won't regret taking the case.
啊 哨兵
Ah, sentry.
约翰・华生医生 前陆军军医
Dr. John Watson, formerly medical officer
隶属波克夏步兵团
attached to the Royal Berkshires,
现在是私人医师
now in civilian practice.
墨斐 副将
Murphy, second in command,
暂时接管麦洛斯步兵团
temporarily in charge of the Royal Mallows,
由于我们上校惨死一事
following the, tragedy of our Colonel's death.
这位一定是福尔摩斯先生?
And this will be Mr. Holmes?
请进
Please.
您能及时赶到真是太好了
It's good of you to come so swiftly.
别客气
Not at all.
我向福尔摩斯解释了您一定
I have explained to Holmes how concerned
为可能形成的丑闻十分忧虑
you must be about the possibility of a scandal.
多谢
Thank you.
我很担心我们团的荣誉
The honor of the regiment is in my care.
但是 报纸上的报道暗示
And yet, the newspapers report suggest
丑闻是不可避免的
that a scandal is inevitable.
当然不会
Surely not.
我已经竭尽全力将记者
I've done my utmost to make sure that reporters
挡在事态之外
were kept as far away as possible.
当然 这样会让他们更加怀疑
Exactly, and that is what has made them suspicious.
他们嗅到了秘密 这会让他们的
They scent a mystery, that much is clear
轻描淡写变成大做文章
from the little they have been able to say.
当然 不应该反反复复
Surely, it would be wrong to repeat,
招惹他们注意...
to draw attention to -
的确
Quite.
我们非常需要您的帮助 福尔摩斯先生
You see how much we need your help, Mr. Holmes.
你觉得如何 福尔摩斯?
What do you say, Holmes?
还能如何?
What can I say?
墨斐少校 您说的都是废话
Major Murphy, you have told me nothing.
我来奥尔德肖特
I have come down here
是受我的朋友劝说
after persuasion from my friend, to Aldershot,
他比我要更热心军队的事
who has more interest in military matters than I.
现在我来了 就请告诉我实情
Now that I am here, please tell me the facts.
本团司令官
The commanding officer of this regiment,
詹姆斯・巴克利上校
Colonel James Barclay,
被发现死在家中
was found dead in his villa
就在前天夜里10点
at about 10 o'clock the night before last.
发现尸体的是列兵贝茨
The body was found by Private Bates,
他的勤务兵 尸体躺在起居室里
his batman, lying in the morning room.
有一条两寸长的不规则伤口
There was a ragged cut, two-inches long,
嵌在他脑后
on the back of his head,
显然是被猛击造成的
which had evidently been caused by a violent blow
凶器是钝器
from a blunt instrument.
尸体旁的地板上
And upon the floor by the body
有根手工制作的木质棍子
was a singular hand-carved wooden club.
还有 沙发上躺着
Also, stretched out on the sofa
晕厥过去的南希・巴...
lying in a dead faint, was Nancy Bar -
巴克利夫人
Mrs. Barclay.
请继续 墨斐少校
Please continue, Major Murphy.
仆人留意到这场悲剧
The servants had been alerted to the tragedy
是因为巴克利上校夫妇
by the sounds of a quarrel
发生了激烈争吵
between the Colonel and Mrs. Barclay.
他们试着闯进起居室
They tried to enter the morning room
却发现门锁上了
but found it locked.
贝茨不得不绕到花园里
Bates had to go around by the garden
从落地窗进去
and get in through the french windows.
而现在您怀疑是巴克利夫人干的?
And now you suspect Mrs. Barclay?
是的
Yes.
但她没能力
But she is quite incapable
做出如此可怕的举动
of such a dreadful act.
我做已故上校
I have been the late Colonel's
的副将很多年了
second in command for a number of years.
我了解南希・巴克利
I've come to know Nancy Barclay well.
当然
Of course.
跟我说说巴克利上校
Tell me about Colonel Barclay,
他是否受到手下士兵们的敬重?
was he highly regarded by the men under his command?
考虑到他的背景 算很敬重了
Considering his background, remarkably so.
他的背景 怎么 他有不光彩的过去?
His background, why, was he ever disgraced?
不 但外界通常不知道
No, but it's not generally known outside
吉姆・巴克利的军旅生涯
that Jim Barclay began his career
始于麦洛斯团普通列兵
as a private soldier in the Mallows.
这是真的?
Did he, indeed?
从列兵晋升到司令官
From private soldier to commanding officer
在同一个团里
in the same regiment,
这可是罕见的成就
that's a rare achievement.
是他在印度叛乱中展现的勇气
I was his gallantry in the Indian Mutiny
让他赢得了这个职位
that got him his commission,
之后的几年他连升三级
and then quite rapid promotion over the years,
我得说 比我快得多
more rapid than mine, for instance.
令人印象深刻
Impressive.
我猜不幸的巴克利夫人被拘留了吧?
And I suppose the unfortunate Mrs. Barclay is in custody?
不 不完全是 不是的
No, not exactly, no.
她在住院 被严密看管
She's in hospital, being looked after,
警官就站在床边
with a police constable standing by.
南希・巴克利现在是个大方的女人
Nancy Barclay is a handsome woman now,
但你应该看看她
but you should have seen her
年轻时在印度 30年前的样子
as a young girl in India, 30 years ago.
她是军团的女儿
She was a daughter of the regiment.
她父亲是团部的军士长 RSM・迪威艾
Her father was the Regimental Sergeant Major, RSM Devoy,
这么个岳父足以吓倒任何士兵
and therefore quite a formidable father-in-law for any soldier.
我记得我们一个连的弟兄
I remember that all the men in my company
都认为她是驻军里最漂亮的女孩
thought her quite the prettiest girl in the garrison.
还是尉官的我 跟她接触不多
As a junior officer I had little to do with her,
但我清楚她是最有魅力
but I was aware that she was a most charming,
最活泼而勇敢的女孩
most vivacious and spirited girl.
理所当然
It was quite understandable
巴克利并非团里唯一一个想
that Barclay was not the only man in the regiment
执子之手的人
who sought her hand.
但最终 她选择了他
But, in the end, he was the one she chose.
他们在伯第结的婚 1858年的夏天
They were married at Bhurtee,
离科尔普不远 之前几个月
not far from Cornpor a few months after
那块被围攻的驻军地
the besieged garrison there
刚被被尼尔将军的纵队解救
was relieved by General Neill's column
时值1858年夏天
in the summer of 1858.
婚后不久
Shortly after the marriage,
巴克利中士不出所料 受到了委任
Sergeant Barclay got his commission, as expected.
巴克利一家
It must have been difficult
起先一定很受危难
for the Barclays at first,
一个军士 在行伍中被晋升
NCO, promoted from the ranks,
作为军士长的女婿?
married to a regimental Sergeant Major's daughter?
是的 我相信的确有些社会摩擦
Yes, I believe there was some little social friction.
但是 南希以高贵和魅力忍耐
But, Nancy carried it off with dignity and charm,
他们很快就被大家接受了
and they gained acceptance in no time.
巴克利的事业蒸蒸日上
Barclay's career flourished,
部队5年前撤出印度
and the regiment returned from India some five years ago.
之后巴克利被委任为司令官
Barclay was then appointed to commanding officer.
他们的婚姻生活仍旧很幸福?
And the marriage continued to be a happy one?
看起来是那样
It appeared to be so.
看起来?
Appeared?
大多数人相信他们的婚姻
Most people believe the marriage
一直是幸福美满的
to have been a uniformly happy one.
那您认为呢 墨斐少校?
And what do you believe, Major Murphy?
作为副将的我
My position as second in command
经常因公拜访巴克利夫妇
often took me to the Barclay's house.
我看到他们婚姻的另一面
I saw a different side to the marriage.
真相的重要性
The truth is more important
远超过您对前任长官的忠诚
than loyalty to your late commander.
有一晚 我在巴克利夫妇家中用餐
One night I had been dining at the Barclays.
出门走到车道尽头
It wasn't until I reached the end of the drive
才发觉自己把雪茄盒
that I realized I'd left my cigar case
落在餐室里了
in the dining room.
我回去的时候 大门还是敞开的
I went back, the front door was still open;
简 那个女仆 在门厅里
Jane, the maid, was in the hall.
真庆幸你还在这儿
I'm glad you're still here,
我把雪茄盒落在桌子上了
I left my cigar case on the table.
我想巴克利上校夫妇
I think the Colonel and Mrs. Barclay
已经就寝了 先生
have gone to bed, sir.
哦 看在上帝的份上 简
Oh, for goodness sake, James.
坦白吧 是谁 谁?
Confess then, who is it, who?
放开我 你弄疼我了
Let go of me, you're hurting me.
那就告诉我你爱我
Tell me you love me then,
只爱我一个人
me and nobody else.
听到我说的吗 听到没有?
Do you hear, do you hear me?
哦 如果不爱你我又为什么嫁给你?
Oh, would I have married you if I didn't?
我不知道 有时候我也想不通
I don't know, sometimes I wonder.
这些猜忌的表现
And this expression of jealousy
墨斐少校 就在您离开他们家
occurred within seconds of you, Major Murphy,
几秒内爆发
leaving the Barclays' house.
告诉我关于上校的事
Tell me about the Colonel,
他是否是个暴力的人?
was he a violent man in any way?
偶尔为之
On occasion.
他会十分残暴地
He could be most vindictive
对付中尉们
towards young subalterns.
但他是一步一步爬到这个位置的
But he'd clawed his way to the top,
走到这步就必须变得残暴
you need to be ruthless to do that.
你肯定他作为司令官
Surely he didn't still feel
不觉得不适应?
out of place as an officer?
不 我不这么认为
No, I don't think so,
但他被一种特殊的抑郁困扰着
but he was subject to a peculiar form of depression.
敬女王
The Queen.
有时在我们讨论以往的战役时
Sometimes when we were discussing old campaigns,
总督 叛乱 阿富汗战争
the premier, the Mutiny, Afghan War,
他会突然笑意尽失
the smile would often be struck from his mouth
像被无形之手扯了下来
as if by some invisible hand.
是的 长期服役于印度
Yes, long service in India
会产生这种症状
can have that effect.
我在波克夏的时候见过
I saw that when I was in the Berkshires.
你提到一根木质棍子
You mentioned a carved wooden club
落在尸体旁
found by the body,
是上校自印度带回来的纪念品吗?
one of the Colonel's Indian souvenirs?
我相信仆人们会说
I believe the servants deny
从未见过这根棍子
ever having seen this club before.
当然 我拜访时也从未见过
Certainly I've never seen it on any of my visits.
它相当的长
It was quite long.
那么警方 我猜
And the police, I suppose,
有没有将其扣押检察?
have retained it for examination?
有
Yes.
他们认为那就是凶器
They believe it to be the murder weapon.
他们这么认为?
Do they, indeed?
我想我们该首先
I think we should begin
动身去巴克利宅
by visiting the Barclays' house,
不过首先 当然
unless, of course,
是否有可能与巴克利夫人面谈?
it is possible to interview Mrs. Barclay?
恐怕她仍在昏迷之中
I'm afraid she's still unconscious.
如我所料
I thought as much.
大卫 大卫
David, David.
多么美妙的早晨啊
What a beautiful morning.
福尔摩斯 是不是巴克利夫人
Holmes, suppose Mrs. Barclay
红杏出墙 上校发现了?
had a lover and the Colonel had found out?
墨斐少校看起来和她相当亲近
Major Murphy seems to have been rather close to her.
你知道 轻微的通奸行为
You know, mild adultery
一直是老生常谈
has always been commonplace
在热带军官夫妇间
among officers and their wives
时有发生
serving in hot climates.
谢谢 华生
Thank you, Watson,
教会了我军队里的道德
for educating me in military morality.
如果真有什么特殊关系
If there had been anything
在墨斐少校和巴克利夫人之间
between Major Murphy and Mrs. Barclay,
他又怎么会提起
would he have related the incident
忘记雪茄盒这件事呢?
of his forgotten cigar case?
大概是在7点半左右 先生
I was about half past seven, sir,
我在餐桌边等着
and I was waiting a table.
巴克利夫人每月的那晚
Once a month, Mrs. Barclay spent
都要去奥尔德肖特做慈善事业
the evening doing charity work in Aldershot.
你这么着急是要去哪里?
Where are you off to in such a hurry?
8点钟开始发放衣物
Well, the distribution of old clothing starts at 8 o'clock,
我向安・莫里森允诺过
and I promised Ann Morrison
我会按时到达工作厅
I'd be at the mission hall on time.
好吧 如果你想因此感染恶疾
Well, if you want to catch some filthy disease
上上下下沾满跳蚤的话
dealing with a lot of flea ridden down and outs,
我想那是你的事
I suppose that's your affair.
我深信人要懂得
I believe in putting back into life
知恩图报
as much as one gets out of it.
我们的命运如此幸运
We've been fortunate with our lot;
其他人就没这么好运了
others haven't been so lucky.
别太晚回来
Don't be late back.
当然不会
Of course not.
巴克利夫人回来的时候
Mrs. Barclay must have returned
一定有9点一刻了 先生
about quarter past nine, sir.
我那时在厨房帮厨师洗盘子
I was in the kitchen helping the cook with the dishes.
远处传来轰轰的雷声
There was thunder in the distance,
我正对范尼夫人说着
and I was just saying to Mrs. Fenning
暴风雨即将来临的时候
that there was a storm brewing,
起居室有人拉铃
when the morning room bell rang.
我上楼后发现巴克利夫人已经归来
I came up here to find that Mrs. Barclay had returned.
她在房间里来回踱步 先生
She was walking up and down this room, sir,
面无血色 心烦意乱
very pale, upset.
她看起来糟透了 先生
She looked awful, sir.
您叫我 夫人?
You rang, madam?
是的 简 给我沏杯茶 好吗?
Yes, Jane, bring me some tea, will you?
好的 夫人
Of course, madam.
简 是你吗?
Jane, is that you?
是的 先生
Yes, sir.
我是否听到了巴克利夫人回来的声音?
Did I hear Mrs. Barclay come in?
是的 先生 她在起居室
Yes, sir, she's in the morning room.
起居室?
The morning room?
是的 先生
Yes, sir.
我正准备去给她泡茶
I'm just about to take her a pot of tea.
茶? 这么晚了她喝茶做什么?
Tea? what does she want tea for at this hour?
我推测 这次
And that, presumably,
是最后有人见到活着的巴克利上校?
was the last time that anyone saw Colonel Barclay alive?
是的 先生
Yes, sir.
你能想到任何原因
Can you think of any reason
让你的女主人大半夜
why your mistress came into this morning room
走进没有炉火的起居室吗?
at that time of night, when the fire was unlit?
不 先生
No, sir.
她经常会出刻意
Did she often make a point
避开上校吗?
of purposely avoiding the Colonel?
你之前听到过他们争吵吗?
Had you ever heard them arguing before?
据我所知没有 先生
Not to my knowledge, sir.
当你从厨房回来
When you returned from the kitchen
端着巴克利夫人的茶
with Mrs. Barclay's tea,
你发现门被锁上了
you found the door locked,
你听到大声的争吵
and you heard voices raised.
你到底听到了什么?
Now, what exactly did you hear?
他们在争吵 先生
They were arguing, sir.
巴克利夫人骂上校是个懦夫
Mrs. Barclay called the Colonel a coward.
她说"这些年来你毁了我的一生"
She said you have ruined my life all these years.
巴克利夫人大喊着"大卫"这个名字
Mrs. Barclay shouted the name "David,"
她喊了两次
she said it twice.
大卫?
David?
你确定吗?
Could you swear to that?
我听得很清楚 先生
I was perfectly clear, sir.
但上校的名字是詹姆斯
But the Colonel's name was James.
你曾经听到
Have you ever heard
巴克利夫人提到过叫大卫的人吗?
Mrs. Barclay refer to anyone called David?
没有 先生 我认为她和上校
No, sir, I don't think she or the Colonel
都不认识任何叫大卫的人
knew anyone by the name of David.
墨斐少校的教名是帕特里克
And Major Murphy's christian name is Patrick.
他们最近有没有叫
Had they had any visitors recently
大卫的访客?
by the name of David?
我想没有 先生
I don't think so, sir.
找到的那根棍子
The club that was found
扔在尸体旁边的
by Colonel Barclay's body,
你以前见过吗?
had you seen it before?
没有 先生
No, sir.
上校有很多印度带回来的战利品
The Colonel had several trophies from India,
但没有那根棍子
but nothing like that club.
你确定吗 斯图尔特小姐?
Are you sure of that, Miss Stewart?
是的 先生
Yes, sir.
我不知道它是从哪来的
I don't know where it came from.
谢谢 我问完了
Thank you, that is all.
哦 不 还有最后一个问题
Oh, no, there is just one last thing,
墨斐少校落在这儿的雪茄盒
Major Murphy once left his cigar case here,
你找到了没有?
did you manage to find it?
找到了 先生
Yes, sir.
上校就躺在这里 先生
The Colonel was lying down here, sir.
头抵着壁炉架?
With his head by the fender?
是的 先生
Yes, sir.
血迹仍清晰可见
You can see the mark of the blood still.
但最恐怖的事 先生 是他的脸
But the most frightening thing of all, sir, was his face.
他的脸?
His face?
当我把他翻过来时
When I rolled him over.
我一看差点吓晕过去
I almost fainted away to look upon it.
他的脸完全扭曲了 非常狰狞
It was all contorted, screwed up,
带着恐惧到极点的表情
with the most horrible look of fear and terror.
就像他预见到自己的死期一样?
As if he'd foreseen his own death?
很有可能 先生
Quite possible, sir.
谢谢你 贝茨
Thank you, Bates.
是什么幻影 什么鬼怪
What apparition, what monster was it
能让上校如此畏惧
that could have frightened the Colonel so.
肯定不是南希・巴克利
Not Nancy Barclay, for sure.
门被反锁了 先生
This door was locked shut, sir,
而且 钥匙不见了
and what's more, the key was missing.
不见了?
Missing?
是的 最后我们不得不
Yes, in the end we had to send
请锁匠来把门打开
for a locksmith to open it.
你们彻底找过那把钥匙吗?
You have made a thorough search for the key?
我们已经掘地三尺了
We searched high and low.
巴克利夫人没拿着
Mrs. Barclay hadn't got it,
也不在上校衣兜里 先生
and it wasn't in the Colonel's pocket, sir.
多谢 范尼夫人
Thank you, Mrs. Fenning.
华生 如果钥匙不在门上
Watson, if the key was not in the door,
也不在巴克利夫人和上校身上 那么...
and neither Mrs. Barclay nor the Colonel had it, then -
屋里肯定有第三个人
Then there must have been a third person.
完全正确
Exactly,
他从落地窗进来 或者出去
who either entered or left through those windows.
这些是贝茨的脚印
These are Bates' footprints.
但这些 是另一个人的脚印
But these, are the footprints of someone else.
有人最近穿越过草地
Someone has recently crossed this lawn,
痕迹非常清晰
the marks are just visible.
他从落地窗进去 又原路出来 华生
He entered and left through those windows, Watson,
我们找对方向了
we're on the right search.
华生 快看这个
Watson, look at this.
这是什么?
What is it?
我们的对手有个不太寻常的伙伴
Our entrant had a somewhat unusual companion.
是只狗 对吧? 有个人养狗
It's a dog, isn't it, somebody's dog?
哪有人听说过会
Whoever heard of a dog
爬上床帘的狗
running up a curtain.
那是不是猫?
What about a cat then?
这些爪印不是猫的
These claw marks are not those of a cat,
也不是猴子 或是任何一种
nor of a monkey, nor of any creature
我们熟悉的生物
that we are familiar with.
我想前后蹄之间的距离
I would think from hind foot to forefoot
至少有15英寸
at least 15 inches.
加上头颈的长度
Add to that the length of neck and head,
这个动物不少于两英尺长
you have a creature no less than two feet,
加上尾巴就更长
more if there's a tail.
它的步幅很奇特
The length of its stride is odd,
这暗示着它
it indicates a creature
背部修长 腿部短小
with a long back and short legs.
像鼬或黄鼠狼之类的动物?
Something like a stoat or a weasel?
同时我们知道它是食肉动物
We also know that it is carnivorous.
你怎么看出来的?
How can you tell that?
你看看它爬上床帘是为什么
Well you see what made it run up the curtain.
金丝雀
The canary.
正是
Exactly.
到底是什么动物?
Then what was this beast?
不 我不能 我不能背叛我的朋友
No, I can't, I cannot betray a friend,
请不要逼我
please don't ask me to.
莫里森小姐
Miss Morrison,
当巴克利夫人前日晚来到这里时
when Mrs. Barclay left her house to come here two nights ago,
她很快乐而满足
she was happy and content.
但两小时后 她回去的时候
When she returned two hours later,
却完全变了样
she was a changed woman.
现在警方怀疑她是凶手
Now the police suspect her of murder.
你有责任澄清你朋友的名声
You owe it to your friend to clear her name.
你必须告诉我那晚什么事
You must tell me what happened last night
彻底改变了她
that so changed her.
很好 我愿意打破沉默
Very well, I shall break my promise of silence
如果真能对她有所帮助
if what I can say can really help her.
的确有事发生
So there was something.
事情十分异乎寻常
It was most bizarre.
我得说我们在这儿见过
I should explain that we come across
各种各样穷困潦倒的人
all sorts of conditions of men here.
然而 那一晚
Yet, the other night,
我看到了从未见过的
I saw the most extraordinary creature
最奇特的一位
I have ever seen.
他不仅驼背
Not only had he a crooked back,
脚还是跛的
but he was lame
走路时曲着膝盖
and walked with his knees bent.
他面色黧黑
His face was darkly tanned,
干瘪褶皱得像烂苹果一样
crinkled and puckered like a withered apple.
那时我想 果真
I thought to myself that truly
这世上还有如此
there are some of us on this earth
不堪重负
who are burdened with more than
被命运遗弃的人
their fair share of misfortune.
更显得奇异的是
This vision was made more unusual
那人还一身东方打扮
by the oriental garb the man was wearing.
我指给南希看
I pointed this person out to Nancy
那个人似乎特别需要帮助
as someone especially deserving of help.
南希那晚精神很不错
Nancy had indeed been in good spirits that evening,
我看到她走近那个男人
and I saw her go towards the man
询问他是否需要照顾
and ask him if he needed assistance.
就是这时候 南希起了变化
It was now that a change came over Nancy.
她与那个男人谈了几句
She had begun a conversation with the man when suddenly
脸色骤然苍白
all the color drained from her face.
看起来像见鬼了似的
She looked as though she had seen a ghost.
那个男人似乎也受到很大影响
The man, too, seemed to be strangely affected
见到她的脸
by the sight of her,
我见他不断使劲挥手
and I saw him gesticulating wildly.
然后 南希和那男人在大厅
Well, Nancy and the man went to a quiet corner
找了个安静角落谈话
of the hall and they talked together
谈了一些时候
for a few moments or so
我听到那个男人一声怒吼
before I heard an angry shout from the man
接着看到他挥舞着拳头 冲出门去
and saw him storm out, waving his fists in the air.
南希 怎么了
Nancy, what is it,
你还好吧?
are you all right?
那个可怜的家伙是谁?
Who was that poor creature?
是我的一个旧相识
It's an old acquaintance of mine
现在落魄了
fallen on hard times.
答应我 安妮 你不会把这事
Promise me, Annie, you won't say anything
告诉任何人 答应我
about this to anyone, promise me.
当然 我答应 只要是你的要求
Of course, I promise, if you so wish.
那这个男人的身份呢?
And the identity of this man?
我猜你就会这么问
I thought you might ask me that.
这件可怕的事发生之后 南希离开了
Well, after this terrible happening, Nancy left.
我自然去问了问
I naturally made a few inquiries
常来的那些人
among some of the regulars;
如此与众不同的人
such an unusual looking creature
当然很引人注意
has of course attracted attention.
原来他是最近从印度回来的老兵
It appears he is an old soldier recently back from India,
谁也不熟悉
and no one knows anything else
他的身世背景
about his background
只知道他是靠
except that he makes a living
给部队逗乐 变戏法
by entertaining the troops, conjuring tricks,
之类手段谋生
that kind of thing.
你对警方提到他了吗?
And did you tell the police about him?
当然没有 一诺千金
Of course not, a promise is a promise.
是的 当然
Yes, of course.
非常感谢 莫里森小姐
Thank you, Miss Morrison.
那就是闯入者的四足小伙伴
That is our intruder's four-footed companion.
是只猫鼬
It's a mongoose.
我想我们找到正主了
I think we've found our man.
我想您就是在印度服役过的亨利・ 伍德先生
Mr. Henry Wood, I believe, late of India.
能和您谈谈吗?
May I have a word?
谈什么?
What about?
关于詹姆斯・巴克利上校被杀一事
A little matter of Colonel James Barclay's death.
她是无辜的 这点你得相信我
She's innocent, you can take my word for it.
那么你是有罪的
Then you are guilty.
不 我没罪
No, I am not guilty.
那么是谁击倒上校的?
Then who struck the Colonel down?
是上天杀了他
It was a just Providence that killed him,
他自己不堪良心重负
his own guilty conscience.
我想你最好解释清楚
I think you'd better explain.
天啊 如果是我打碎他的脑壳
My God, if I had smashed his head in,
像我企盼已久的那样
as it was in my heart to do,
那也是他欠我的
he would have got only what he deserved from me.
不 我没碰过他一根手指头
No, I never laid a hand on him,
根本不劳我动手
I was spared the trouble.
让我讲讲我的故事
I'll tell you my story.
我对此丝毫不感到耻辱
There is no cause for me to be ashamed of it.
你们看到现在的我 背驼得像骆驼
You see me now with my back like a camel,
肋骨也七扭八歪
my ribs all awry,
但从前的亨利・伍德下士
but there was a time when Corporal Henry Wood
可是麦洛斯团最潇洒的人
was the smartest man in the Royal Mallows.
你和巴克利上校同属一个团?
You were in the same regiment as Colonel Barclay?
哦 是的 但那是他还是吉姆・巴克利中士
Oh, yes, but he was Sergeant Jim Barclay then.
我们同属一个连
We were in the same company,
我们还有另一个相同点
and we had something else in common,
都深深爱着
we were both in love
同一个女人 南希・迪威艾
with the same woman, Nancy Devoy.
她父亲是
Who was the daughter
团部军士长
of the Regimental Sergeant Major.
两个男人深爱着她
There were two men who loved her,
但她只爱其中的一个
but only one whom she loved.
她...你们一定觉得可笑吧
She you'll laugh when you look at
这炉火前蜷缩的可怜虫
this poor thing huddled in front of the fire
敢自称是我英俊的外表
and hear me say that it was for my good looks
赢得了南希的爱
that Nancy loved me.
她一直以来爱的是我
I was the one she loved all along.
但尽管我占据了她的心
But although I had her heart,
她父亲却不赞成
her father didn't approve of me.
我虽然是个不拘小节 有些鲁莽的人
I was a harum-scarum, reckless sort of lad,
但我同时也是忠心耿耿 非常坦率
but I was always honest and plain dealing as well.
哦 南希的父亲希望她嫁给巴克利
Oh, Nancy's father wanted her to marry Barclay.
他谨言慎行
He was careful to keep out of trouble,
总是见机行事
always did the right thing,
不像我这样 常带南希
not like me who took Nancy
去他父亲不喜欢的地方
to places her father didn't like.
此外 巴克利受过教育
Besides, Barclay had had an education,
就快要升为军官了
he was already marked for the sword-belt.
迪威艾自然觉得巴克利
RSM Devoy naturally thought Barclay
和他女儿才是门当户对
the better match for his daughter.
但她对我真心实意
But she remained true to me,
我们本来要结婚了
and we would have married
如果不是那场暴动的话
had it not been for the Mutiny.
为什么南希・迪威艾没嫁给所爱之人?
Why did Nancy Devoy not marry the man she loved?
那是1857的雨季
It was monsoon time in 1857,
当印度土兵对英国宣战之时
when the Sepoys rose up against the British.
我们团在伯第被狙击
The regiment was shut up in Bhurtee.
一万多叛军把我们团团围住
There were 10,000 rebels round us,
密不透风 铁桶一般
pinning us down like terriers round a rat cage.
我们渐渐弹尽粮绝
We'd run short of food and ammunition,
必须联系上尼尔将军正向
we had to communicate with General Neill's column
内地进军的纵队
that was moving up-country.
这是唯一的获救方法
It was our only chance to get help.
我们连的司令官希望有志愿者
Our company commander had asked for a volunteer,
一个机灵强壮的战士潜出营地
a fit, strong soldier to slip out of the garrison
趁着夜色通风报信
at dead of night and make contact
找到平原上的救援纵队
with the relief column out on the plain beyond.
像傻子一样 我主动请缨
Like a fool, I volunteered.
那是个危险重重的任务
It was a dangerous mission all right,
千百条生命处于危险之中
there were a 1,000 lives in peril.
但我只牵挂其中的一个...
But I was thinking of only one of them...
南希・迪威艾
Nancy Devoy,
我深爱的女人 世上最美丽
the woman I loved, and the finest girl
最生机勃勃的女人
that ever had the breath of life between her lips.
和她道别是最难的一环
Saying goodbye to her was the hardest thing.
我们交换了定情信物 没想到
As we exchanged mementos, I never thought that
这一别就是30年
I was saying goodbye to her for 30 years.
是我追求南希的情敌
It was my rival for Nancy's hand
送我上的路
who saw me off on my journey
深夜穿越敌军封锁线
through the enemy lines that night,
巴克利中士
Sergeant Barclay.
他说他对驻地
He said he knew the lie of the land
周边地形再清楚不过
around the garrison better than any other.
当我志愿寻找救援的时候
While I volunteered to make the journey,
吉姆・巴克利自愿指引我
Jim Barclay volunteered to advise me
最佳行动路径
on the best route to take.
那之后
So, just after then,
在战友的炮火掩护下
while my comrades gave me covering fire,
我出发了
I set off.
巴克利告诉我沿着溪流
Barclay had told me to follow a stream
向一个小峡谷走
which would lead to a gully.
他说 这是最安全的下山途径
This, he said, was the safest way downhill.
他的指引很有用
His directions were perfect
我很快就涉过刺骨的河水
and soon I was wading through icy water
那里昨天还是喜马拉雅山脉的积雪
that only the day before had been snow in the Himalayas.
我能看到叛军的营帐和灯火
I could see the lights and fires in the rebels' camp
但我隐藏得很好
but I kept well down,
躲过了哨兵的视线
out of sight of their sentry posts.
我到了小峡谷后 自认为安全了
I came to the gully and thought I was safe.
紧接着 我被袭击了
Then it happened, I was attacked.
重物击中了我的头部
Something hard cracked down on my head
之后就不省人事了
and everything spun around.
当我醒来之后 我被绑得像只鸡一样
When I came to, I was trussed up like a chicken
还被挂在树上
and hanging from a tree.
我的手臂像是生生从
My arms felt as though they were being wrenched
关节处扯了开来
out of their sockets.
我不在乎疼痛 我最痛心的
I didn't mind the pain, but I was sick at heart
是没能完成任务
for having failed in my mission.
那些等待救助的人
What would be the fate of those
他们的命运会如何呢?
I had been trying to save?
但最大的震惊是 从我能听懂的
But the biggest blow came as I listened
叛军口中说出的一些字眼
to what I could understand of a rebels' talk.
我发现自己被出卖了
I heard enough to realize that I had been betrayed.
指引我方向的那个人
The very man who had shown me the way to take
居然把我出卖给敌人
had betrayed me to the enemy.
巴克利不惜除掉我
Barclay had got rid of me
只为得到我的女孩
to make sure he could have my girl.
现在 你们知道了詹姆斯・巴克利的心狠手辣
Now, you know what James Barclay was capable of.
原来尼尔将军的纵队
Well, it turned out that General Neill's column
已经在救援伯第的路上了
was already on its way to relieve Bhurtee.
叛军撤退了
The rebels retreated,
他们带走了我
they dragged me away with them.
百般折磨我
I was tortured.
我试图逃跑 又被抓住折磨
I tried to escape, I was tortured again.
又隔了多少年啊
It was to be many a long year
我才再次看到一张白人的脸
before I saw another white face.
俘虏我的人逃向北方 进入了深山
My captors fled north, further into the hills,
把我当做奴隶
and used me as a sort of slave.
我过着猪狗不如的生活
I was treated worse than a dog
这些混蛋几乎折断了我每一根骨头
and they damn near broke every bone in my body.
有时我更希望他们杀了我
Sometimes I'd wish they'd just killed me,
但我对那个毁我一生的人的厌恶
but my thoughts of hatred and loathing for the man
和仇恨支撑着我
who destroyed my life kept me going.
我每天都想着报复巴克利
I dreamed of revenge on Barclay.
一天 阿富汗部落的人
One day some Afghan tribesmen
杀死了看守我的叛军
murdered the rebels that held me prisoner.
把我留在那儿自生自灭
They left me for dead, too.
但奇迹发生了 我依旧活着
But by a miracle, I still lived.
于是 我像对向那些对我施暴的人复仇
So, I had my revenge on my torturers,
但巴克利早就不知去向
but Barclay was beyond my grasp.
至于南希
And what of Nancy,
我不知她是生是死
I had no means of knowing whether she was alive or dead.
我流浪回到旁遮普(印度)
I wandered back to the Punjab,
住在土人中间
and lived among the natives,
靠耍些把戏为生
picking up a living by the conjuring tricks
我跟随街头魔术师学了不少
I'd learned from the street magicians.
何必奢望呢 我一个瘸子
What use was it for me, a wretched cripple,
就算乘船回到英格兰
to get passage back by ship to England
和团里的老战友重聚 又有什么用?
and make myself known to my old comrades in the regiment?
向吉姆・巴克利复仇的怒焰也没能让我这么做
Even revenge on Jim Barclay didn't make me go.
不 我...直说吧
No, I I'll tell you straight,
我更希望我的南希和麦洛斯团的
I preferred my Nancy and my old pals
老战友们继续相信
in the Royal Mallows to go on believing
亨利・伍德已经英勇牺牲
that Harry Wood died a hero's death
直着腰杆而死
with a straight back,
不愿让他们看我屈膝弓背
than see him crawling about the world
像猩猩一样爬行 不成人形
more like a chimpanzee than a human being.
但你还是回来了
But you did return,
回到你团部驻扎的奥尔德肖特 为什么?
and to Aldershot where your old regiment was stationed, why?
我只想在死前再看看故乡
I just wanted to see the old country once more before I died.
我省吃俭用 终于坐船出发了
I saved what I could and eventually I got a ship.
我不知道团部仍驻扎在奥尔德肖特
I didn't know the regiment was stationed here in Aldershot,
我只想回到战士们的驻地
I just wanted to be where there were soldiers.
我可以到各处的餐厅讨生活
I could earn my keep going around the canteens
变戏法逗他们乐
doing my tricks to entertain them.
我不再想杀了巴克利
I no longer wanted to kill Barclay,
复仇之火
the fires of revenge
在时间的历练下已所剩无几
had burned low over the years...
直到我见到她
until I saw her.
我觉得我应该更英国化些
I thought I'd better get some English tongs,
我已经很滑稽了
I looked comical enough without wearing
不能再穿这些异国的衣服
these foreign clothes the whole time.
起先 我专心致志挑一件
At first, I was more interested in finding
厚点的外套 不大在乎
a thick overcoat than looking at the charity
分发物品的慈善女士们
ladies who were doling them out.
之后她们中的一个走过来
Then one of them came over,
我立刻认出了她
I recognized her at once,
她几乎没变 还是那么漂亮
she'd hardly changed, still beautiful.
更令我惊奇的是她...
What's more amazing is she -
她好像认识我
she seemed to know me.
晚上好 我能帮助你吗?
Good evening, can I help you?
你找到需要的...
Have you been able to find anything that -
很抱歉 我以为...
I'm sorry, I thought I...
南希 是我啊 亨利
Nancy, it is me, Harry.
别被我吓到
Don't be afraid.
我以为你死了30年了
I thought you had been dead these 30 years.
我的确死过了...
I have been...
我以为我再也见不到你了
I thought I would never see you again.
我们聊了一会
We spoke for a moment or two together.
我告诉她一些我的事
I told her some of my story.
我不该告诉她
I should have spared telling her
她的丈夫是个叛徒
that her husband was a traitor
但我冲昏了头 脱口而出
but it all came pouring out of me,
30年入骨的恨啊
30 years of hate.
她被我的话震惊了
She was so effected by what I said,
我无法忍受下去
I couldn't stand it.
就逃了出去
I went outside,
之后我看到她走出工作厅
then I saw her come out of the mission
于是我便跟踪到她家
and I followed her home.
我见她走进那所房子 一盏灯亮了
I saw her go into the house, a light came on.
我看着她坐在椅子上
I saw her sitting in a chair.
之后他走进那间房间
And then he came into the room.
詹姆斯 我得跟你谈谈
James, I have to talk to you.
你干嘛锁门
Why are you locking that door.
我说过 别太晚回来
Don't be back late, I said,
别太晚回来 听见没?
don't be back late, didn't I?
你外面有男人
You've been with someone.
不...
No -
你背着我找男人
You have been with someone.
没有...
No -
到底是谁?
Who is it?
你毁了我的一生
...you've ruined my life.
这么多年 这么多年来
All these years, all these years.
哦 你怎能做出这么...
Oh, how could you do such a thing -
巴克利夫人 您的茶
Mrs. Barclay, your tea.
这么残忍的事
it was evil.
我恨你 我恨你 我恨你 我恨你
I hate you, I hate you, I hate you, I hate you.
不
No-
看到他抓住她的手
To see him lay a hand on her
我愤怒到了极点
made me mad with anger.
我的情感战胜了一切
My feelings overcame me -
大卫
David -
您的茶 夫人
Your tea, madam.
大卫 你背叛了他
David, you betrayed him.
这不是真的
It's not true.
但他还活着 我告诉你 我见到他了
But he's alive, I tell you, I've seen him.
你说谎 你疯了
You're lying, you're mad.
我从未见过一个人有那种表情
He looked as I have never seen a man look.
我清楚的感受到他脸上死亡的气息
I read death on his face as plain as anything.
我的突然出现像一颗子弹
The bare sight of me was like a bullet
打穿了他负罪的心
through his guilty heart.
巴克利夫人 巴克利夫人 快开门
Mrs. Barclay, Mrs. Barclay, open the door.
他撞上了壁炉架
He smashed onto the fender.
他在倒下去之前就死了
He was dead before he fell.
巴克利夫人 巴克利夫人 快开门
Mrs. Barclay, Mrs. Barclay, open the door.
我从南希手中拿走了钥匙
I took the key to the door from Nancy's hand,
本想开门求救
intending to open it and get help.
转念一想我得快点逃走
I thought I'd better get away
不然就再也洗不清了
or things might look black against me.
匆忙中 我一边把钥匙揣进口袋里
In haste, I thrust the key into my pocket
一边抓回逃出笼子
whilst I was chasing Teddy,
爬上床帘的泰迪
who'd escaped from his box and run up a curtain.
泰迪
Teddy.
所以 上校是死于
So, the Colonel died before
撞到壁炉架之前?
he struck his head on the fender?
因为突然的震惊 导致中风猝死
An apoplectic fit, brought on by shock.
伍德先生 假设法医也
Mr. Wood, provided the coroner reaches
得到相同的结论 那么巴克利夫人
the same conclusion, Mrs. Barclay -
南希
Nancy.
就会被释放
will be free.
我相信您也不会反对把
I trust you would have no objection
整件事复述给警方吧
to repeating your story to the police,
一旦需要的话?
should the need arise?
福尔摩斯先生 南希现在如何?
Mr. Holmes, how is Nancy?
她人在医院
She's in hospital.
据我所知 她一定会恢复健康
I understand in time she should make a complete recovery.
谢天谢地
Thank God.
嗨 安 真高兴见到你
Hello, Ann, how lovely to see you.
你好点了吗?
Are you better?
是的 我好多了
Yes, I'm much better.
福尔摩斯 只有一件事我还不明白
Holmes, there's just one thing I don't understand.
如果上校的名字是詹姆斯
If the Colonel's name was James,
而伍德被称呼为亨利或哈利
and Wood was called either Henry or Harry,
那大卫又是谁?
then who the deuce was David?
我亲爱的华生
My dear Watson,
大卫这个名字本应告诉我
that name David should have told me
整个故事 如果我真是你喜欢描述的
the whole story had I been the ideal reasoner,
推理大师的话
which you are so fond of depicting.
可是 唉 我没能推断到
But alas, my powers of deduction failed.
你瞧 大卫 在这里
You see, David, in this case,
是一种谴责之辞
was evidently used as a term of reproach.
谴责?
Reproach?
你不记得大卫王怎样
Don't you remember how King David
把赫梯族的乌利亚送到战场
sent Uriah the Hittite into the forefront
最前线送死 以便有机会
of the battle to die so that he might
夺取他的女人 拔示巴了吗?
steal his woman, Bathsheba?
我想这个故事
I think you will find the story
你会在撒母耳记上篇或下篇中找到
in the first or second book of Samuel.
我对旧约记不太清了
My old testament is a little rusty.
说的不错 福尔摩斯
You're quite right, Holmes,
撒母耳记下篇 11:14-17
Il Samuel, 11:14-17.
你显然已经查过了
You appear to have looked it up yourself
就在我们从奥尔德肖特回来之后
since we returned home from Aldershot.
你是怎么知道的?
How did you know?
你把这张我们在滑铁卢餐厅
You used this bill for our meal
的账单当作书签 不是吗?
at Waterloo as a bookmarker, did you not?
漂亮 华生
Excellent, Watson.
雕虫小技 我亲爱的福尔摩斯
Elementary, my dear Holmes.
晚安 老伙计
Goodnight, old fellow.
破烂熊字幕组 -==www.RagBear.com==- 欢迎加入